# Martin Jung | Curriculum Vitae

ESM Programm, IIASA, Laxenburg, A-2361, Austria

← +43 2236 807 316
► ☐ martinjung@zoho.com
ⓒ martin-jung.github.io
in jungmartin
• ☐ Martin-Jung

Widely interested in (Macro-)Ecology, Conservation Biology and Sustainability Science with regards to global change. Specialist in data science, remote-sensing analysis and interpreting spatial data. Many years of experience in project management and providing quantitative solutions to environmental problems.

# **Career history**

Paid employment.....

# International Institute for Applied Systems Analysis (IIASA)

Laxenburg, Austria

Postdoctoral Research scholar

April 2019–present

Developing new global integrated biodiversity, carbon and ecosystem services maps and models using global data aggregation and optimisation routines

### **University of Sussex**

Brighton, UK

<sup>°</sup> Associate doctoral tutor

January 2017–March 2019

Assisted in the teaching and marking of biology and geography courses for BSc and MSc students. Led one day intensive workshops in GIS & data analysis for graduate students.

#### Lund university - Centre for Sustainability studies

Lund, Sweden

Č Research assistant

*February 2015–September 2015* 

Worked for the AGROMES project (funded by the Swedish research council) mapping the environmental, economic, and social tradeoffs of European farming systems across scales. Involved the acquisition, manipulation, analysis and visualisation of economic and environmental data. Collaboration with the University of British Columbia and Sussex University

### Imperial College London

London, UK

External database contractor

October 2014–August 2015

Developed, implemented and administrated a spatially explicit relational database (PostgreSQL & PostGIS) for the BIOFRAG project. Wrote parsing scripts and SQL queries for database maintenance.

### University of Copenhagen

Copenhagen, Denmark

Laboratory assistant

*May 2013–April 2015* 

Laboratory and field work as well as statistical analyses in biological pest control (Fruitgrowth, Softpest, INBIOsoil) projects.

#### gaiac - research institute

Aachen, Germany

Research assistant

September 2012-October 2012

GIS and statistical analyses around the Virtual Forest project and urban ecology. Conducted plant vegetation surveys on windfall calamity areas.

### Solarenergie-Förderverein Deutschland e.V.

Aachen, Germany

<sup>°</sup> Part-time database maintainer

*July 2006–May 2013* 

Database maintenance and user support of the largest database for solar panel owners in Germany.

# Internships & Volunteer activities.....

### Helmholtz-Zentrum für Umweltforschung - UFZ

Leipzig, Germany

<sup>'</sup> Internship

September 2011–October 2011

GIS analyses for habitat connectivity and restoration.

#### SAVE wildlife conservation fund

Wülfrath, Germany

Volunteer project leader

May 2011–September 2012

Responsible for coordinating social media and stake holder interactions in Cameroon and the USA.

### University of Marburg

Bialowieza Forest, Poland

<sup>°</sup> Volunteer

Spring 2011 & Summer 2012

Assistance in ornithological field surveys in temperate forests.

#### **NLWKN**

Langeoog, Germany

<sup>'</sup> Assistant national park ranger

July 2008-June 2009

Ornithological surveys & public relation including giving public tours and seminars.

### **Education**

#### PhD in Environmental Sciences

University of Sussex, UK

Pass without corrections

September 2015- March 2019

Specialising in big data, remote sensing & statistical analyses

#### MSc in Biology

University of Copenhagen, Denmark

12 (A)

2013-2015

Specialisation in Macroecology & African land systems. Four months of self-organised fieldwork in Tanzania and Kenya

#### **BSc** in Biology

University of Marburg, Germany

) 1.9 (A)

2009–2012

Specialising in Conservation ecology. Six months of fieldwork in east Poland.

# Professional skills

Languages: Fluent in German & English, basic literacy in Danish.

**General:** Very good project- and time-management skills. Experienced in giving presentations, working well solo or in teams.

**Statistics:** Univariate and multivariate statistics. Time series analyses. Linear optimizations. Good knowledge about applying Bayesian and modern machine learning techniques.

Coding: Proficient in: R, Python, Bash, Javascript, SQL, HTML, CSS, TeX, Learning Julia

Databases: MySQL, PostgreSQL, PostGIS, SQLite, Microsoft Access.

**General computer skills:** Broad Linux & Microsoft Windows knowledge. Most existing GIS software. Comfortable with big data. Cloud computing knowledge (Google Cloud, Google Earth Engine, AWS). Excellent command of Microsoft Office.

# **Publications**

Peer reviewed...

- [1] **Jung, M.**, Scharlemann, J. P. W. and Rowhani, P. (accepted). Landscape-wide changes in land use and land cover correlate with, but rarely explain local biodiversity change *Landscape Ecology*
- [2] **Jung, M.**, Raj Dahal, P., Butchart, S. H. M., Donald, P.F., De Lamo, X., Lesiv, M., Kapos, V., Rondinini, C. and Visconti, P. (2020). A global map of terrestrial habitat types *Nature Scientific data* 7(1),256 doi:10.1038/s41597-020-00599-8
- [3] **Jung, M.**, Rowhani, P., and Scharlemann, J. P. W. (2019). Impacts of past abrupt land change on local biodiversity globally. *Nature Communications*, 10(1), 5474. doi:10.1038/s41467-019-13452-3
- [4] **Jung, M.**, Rowhani, P., Newbold, T., Bentley, L., Purvis, A. and Scharlemann, J. P.W. (2019) "Local species assemblages are influenced more by past than current dissimilarities in photosynthetic activity" *Ecography*, 42(4), 670–682. doi:10.1111/ecog.04031
- [5] Kehoe, L., [...], **Jung, M.**, *et al.* (2019) "Make EU trade with Brazil sustainable" *Science*, 364(6438):341 doi:10.1126/science.aaw8276
- [6] Norfolk, O., **Jung, M.**, Platts, P. J., Malaki, P., Odeny, D., and Marchant, R. (2017) "Birds in the matrix: the role of agriculture in avian conservation in the Taita Hills, Kenya." *African Journal of Ecology*, doi:10.1111/aje.12383
- [7] **Jung, M.**, Hill, S. L. L., Platts, P. J., Marchant, R., Siebert, S., Fournier, A., Munyekenye, F. B., Purvis, A., Burgess, N. D. and Newbold, T. (2017) "Local factors mediate the response of biodiversity to land use on two African mountains." *Animal Conservation*, doi:10.1111/acv.12327
- [8] Hudson, L., [...], **Jung, M.** *et al.* (2017) "The database of the PREDICTS (Projecting Responses of Ecological Diversity In Changing Terrestrial Systems) project." *Ecology and Evolution*, 7(1), 145-188. doi:10.1002/ece3.2579
- [9] Newbold, T., [...], **Jung**, **M.** *et al.* (2016) "Has land use pushed terrestrial biodiversity beyond the planetary boundary? A global assessment." *Science*, 353(6296):288-291 doi:10.1126/science.aaf2201
- [10] Martin, P.A., **Jung**, **M.**, Brearley, F.Q., Ribbons, R.R., Lines, E.R. and Jacob, A.L. (2016) "Can we set a global threshold age to define mature forests?" *PeerJ*, e1595 doi:10.7717/peerj.1595
- [11] **Jung, M.** (2015) "LecoS A python plugin for automated landscape ecology analysis." *Ecological Informatics* 31: 18-21 doi:10.1016/j.ecoinf.2015.11.006
- [12] Hudson, L., [...], **Jung, M.** [...] *et al.* (2014) "The PREDICTS database: a global database of how local terrestrial biodiversity responds to human impacts" *Ecology and Evolution*; 4(24):4701-4735 doi:10.1002/ece3.1303

Submitted or in review.

[13] **Jung, M.**, Arnell, A., de Lamo, X., García-Rangel, S., Lewis, M., Mark, J., Merow, C., Miles, L., Ondo, I., Pironon, S., Ravilious, C., Rivers, M., Schepashenko, D., Tallowin, O., van Soesbergen,

- A., Govaerts, R., Boyle, B.L., Enquist, B.J., Feng, X., Gallagher, R. V, Maitner, B., Meiri, S., Mulligan, M., Ofer, G., Hanson, J.O., Jetz, W., Di Marco, M., McGowan, J., Rinnan, D.S., Sachs, J.D., Lesiv, M., Adams, V., Andrew, S.C., Burger, J.R., Hannah, L., Marquet, P.A., McCarthy, J.K., Morueta-Holme, N., Newman, E.A., Park, D.S., Roehrdanz, P.R., Svenning, J.-C., Violle, C., Wieringa, J.J., Wynne, G., Fritz, S., Strassburg, B.B.N., Obersteiner, M., Kapos, V., Burgess, N., Schmidt-Traub, G., Visconti, P., (in review). Areas of global importance for terrestrial biodiversity, carbon, and water. doi:10.1101/2020.04.16.021444
- [14] Monjeau, A., [...], **Jung, M.** et al. (in review) Joint prioritization of biodiversity conservation, ecosystem services supply and food production in Argentina
- [15] Fastre, C., Mogg, S., **Jung, M.**, and Visconti, P. (in review). Targeted expansion of Protected Areas to maximise the persistence of terrestrial mammals. *Conservation Biology* doi:10.1101/608992v2
- [16] Santini, L., Antao, L., Benítez-López, A., Dornelas, M., Di Marco, M., Haghkerdar, J.M., Jones, F., **Jung, M.**, Rapacciuolo, G. and González-Suárez M. (in review). Macroecology and Conservation Biology: links, challenges, and opportunities *BioScience*

Other

- Waldron, A., [...], **Jung, M.**, *et al.* (2020) Protecting 30% of the planet for nature: costs, benefits and economic implications *Working paper for the post-2020 Global Biodiversity Framework* Protecting 30% of the planet for nature: costs, benefits and economic implications
- Jung, M., Visconti, P., De Lamo, X., Tallowin, O. and Mark, J. (2020) How we save the World -Protection Priorities National Geographic Magazine, Issue 4 - Earth Day 50th Anniversary special issue - Online
- Tomislav, H., **Jung, M.** and Visconti, P. (2020) Potential distribution of land cover classes (Potential Natural Vegetation) at 250 m spatial resolution (Version v0.1) Zenodo. doi:10.5281/zenodo.3631254
- Jung, M. (2014) "QSDM Species distribution modelling support for the QGIS Processing toolbox", Download link
- **Jung, M.** (2012) "The U.S.-Investors and African palm oil, Report for the SAVE Wildlife Conservation Fund Download link

### **Presentations**

Talks.....

- [1] **Jung, M.** and Visconti P. (2020) "Global Areas Of Importance For Species Conservation And Carbon Storage", *World Biodiversity Forum*, February 23-28, Davos, Switzerland.
- [2] **Jung, M.** and Visconti P. (2019) "Identifying global terrestrial areas of biodiversity significance", *UNEP-WCMC Gaining consensus on biodiversity assessments workshop*, May 20-24, Cambridge, UK.
- [3] **Jung, M.**, Rowhani, P. and Scharlemann, J. (2018) "Using remote sensing to assess biotic lag in species assemblages globally", *British Ecological Society Annual Meeting*, December 17-19, Birmingham, UK.
- [4] **Jung, M.** (2018) "Linking local biodiversity change and landscape-wide land changes", *Macroe-cology SIG: Annual Meeting 2018 British Ecological Society*, July 10-11, St. Andrews, UK.

- [5] **Jung, M.** (2017) "The lasting impact of past major disturbances on biodiversity", *Macroecology SIG: Annual Meeting 2017 British Ecological Society*, July 5-7, London, UK.
- [6] **Jung, M.** (2016) "The local and African-wide distinctiveness of agroforestry for biodiversity", *Evolution, behaviour and environment seminar series*, October 27, Sussex, UK.
- [7] **Jung, M.** (2016) "Influence of land dynamics on biodiversity", *Evolution, behaviour and environment seminar series*, April 30, Sussex, UK.
- [8] **Jung, M.**, Newbold, T. and Burgess N.D. (2014) "African species' response to land-use change. Assessing the match between an Africa-wide model and fine-scale field data", 7th Early Career Research meeting of the Tropical Ecology Group British Ecological Society, August 14- 15, York, UK.

Posters

- [9] Jung, M., Raj Daha, P., Butchart, Donald, P.F., Rondini, C. and Visconti, P. (2020) "A Global Map Of Species Terrestrial Habitat Types", World Biodiversity Forum, February 23-28, Davos, Switzerland Download link
- [10] **Jung, M.**, Rowhani, P. and Scharlemann, J. (2017) "Abrupt land change events alter biodiversity", *University of Sussex Annual research symposium*, December 14- 15, Sussex, UK. **Best poster prize**
- [11] **Jung, M.**, Rowhani, P. and Scharlemann, J. (2016) "Lasting influences of past land-surface conditions on species assemblages", *British Ecological Society Annual Meeting*, December 11- 14, Liverpool, UK. **Highly commended** <u>Download link</u>
- [12] **Jung, M.**, Burgess, N.D. and Newbold, T. (2016) "A comparison of broad-scale model estimates with independent bird data from East-Africa", *Student Conference on Conservation Science*, March 22-24, Cambridge, UK. <u>Download link</u>
- [13] **Jung, M.**, Newbold, T. and Burgess, N.D. (2014) "African species' response to land-use change. Assessing the match between an Africa-wide model and fine-scale field data", 7th Early Career Research meeting of the Tropical Ecology Group British Ecological Society, August 14- 15, York, UK. Download link
- [14] Linder J.M., Gorschlüter L., Altherr, S., Waltert, M., **Jung, M.** (not on abstract), Chapple, A. and Astaras C. (2012) "The anatomy of an oil palm plantation and why African primate diversity is in trouble", 2012 Annual Meeting of the American Association of Physical Anthropologists, April 11- 14, Portland, Oregon.

# Academic service

2019 - present **Associate Editor** for Diversity and Distributions.

Reviewer for multiple academic journals in Ecology, Environmental Science and Remote Sensing. See **here** for (incomplete) list.

# Teaching experience

2018 - QGIS workshop for postgraduates - University of Sussex, UK

2018 - Introduction to Geographical Information systems - University of Sussex, UK

- 2017 Tutor on R course for PhD, MSc and BSc students R4ALL, UK
- 2016-19 Introduction to Ecology and Conservation University of Sussex, UK
- 2015 Tutoring on Workshop "Landscape Ecology analysis in QGIS" University of Lund, Sweden
- 2014 Workshop "Vegetation from space and from the ground" African Insect Science for Food and Health (ICIPE), Kenya
- 2013 Workshop "Landscape Ecology analysis in QGIS" University of Lund, Sweden

# Professional development

- 2017 Two weeks summer school on synthesising and modelling biodiversity data iDiv, Germany
- 2016 Multiple training courses on academic writing, teaching and entrepreneurial thinking and policy impact University of Sussex Doctoral school, UK

# Successful Grants and awards

- 2018 Doctoral festival runner up research image prize in the category science. Volume 120 £ (140 €)
- 2015 University of Sussex Researcher led initiative fund for setting up a quantitative analysis group Volume: 1000 £ (1416 €)
- 2015-2019 University of Sussex school of life sciences PhD funding grant Volume: 14.057 £ (19910 €) annually
- 2014 DANIDA Travel Grant (No. A26811) in support of conducting fieldwork in Kenya and Tanzania Volume: 13000 DKK (1700 €)
- 2013-2014 Monthly scholarship from the Danish ministry of Higher Education and Science Volume: 5753 DKK (770 €) monthly
- 2013 Grant to extent the functionality of my QGIS plugin LecoS from the Universidade de Évora, Departamento de Biologia, Unidade de Biologia da Conservação Volume: 250 €

# **Professional References**

Available on request